Now today's דף *daf* is מ"א *Mem Aleph*, 41, and we pick
up with the משנה mishna *Mishna* at the bottom of מ"א עמוד
ב' *Mem Amud Bet*. If you remembered, we were talking about what
makes כשר מצה matzah, *kosher matzah* כשר מרור *kosher maror*, but then
we turned back to חמץ chametz. *chametz* concerns about bran and water
and similar issues.
And now the משנה mishna *mishna*, as you will see, continues with
חמץ chametz *chametz* concerns but seems to double back. Let's read the
משנה mishna *mishna* here at the bottom of מ"א עמוד א' *Mem
Amud Aleph*. אין נותנים קמח לתוך חרוסת charoset *Ein notnim kemach letoch
charoset*. So the same way we had talked about water and bran
and different types of things people might make not in the process
of exactly making bread,
but in making other products, making stuff to feed to your chickens
or things to put on your wounds, so and nevertheless there are
obvious חמץ chametz *chametz* concerns when you mix in with them grains
or flour. So here too the משנה mishna *mishna* says you don't
put flour into חרוסת charoset *charoset*, which does not necessarily mean the
חרוסת charoset, *charoset* of the סדר *Seder* night. I mean, it might
be the same type of dish, but it basically means, as רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says, some type of a dip that you would use
for dipping meat and it would have in it
vinegar and you would put in flour in order to thicken it.
So again, this is going to get to the question about whether
vinegar prevents the process of becoming חמץ chametz *chametz*. So the משנה
Mishnah *mishna* says you don't put flour into this dip או o,
לתוך חרדל *o letoch chardal*, or into mustard. Mustard that we have
is not a spice per se; it's made out of mustard seed,
and I don't know exactly the ingredients of mustard, I didn't look
it up, but it is some type of mustard seed and vinegar
and other types of things. So you might put in flour into
that as well as a type of a thickening agent or something,
and it says don't do that. So again, it's a question of
flour with liquid but also with the presence of vinegar.
The question came the other day what was the vinegar made out
of, and the vinegar in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* seems to be
always referring to wine vinegar. So the vinegar itself is not a
wheat product and it's liquid, but the question is again, does it
have the ability to
actually stall or prevent fermentation?
So that's continuing in that theme about mixing flour or grains with
other things. And then ואם נתן יאכל מיד yachel miyad, *v'im natan
yochal miyad*. If you did go ahead and did it, eat it
immediately. So presumably,
it won't immediately become חמץ chametz *chametz*, so if you pop it
right in your mouth, that's okay. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אוסר *Rabbi
Meir oser*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says no, actually as
soon as you did this, it's problematic and it might become חמץ
chametz *chametz* even immediately and you can't eat it, you have to
destroy it. Okay, so that's ending up that theme. Now we seem
to double back to the issues of מצה matzah *matzah* and of
מצה matzah. *matzah* and מרור *maror*, because when we mentioned מצה matzah
*matzah* and מרור *maror*, there was one food that we didn't mention,
which was—what was
the
food we eat פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, the קרבן פסח korban Pesach, *korban
Pesach*, right? Which raises the question, as I said, based on an
earlier discussion about מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni*, whatever, are we talking about
מצה matzah. *matzah* and מרור *maror* nowadays, or are we talking about
the מצה matzah, *matzah* and מרור *maror* of the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*
of the סדר *Seder* of the קרבן פסח korban Pesach. *korban Pesach*
when they were more accompaniments to the פסח Pesach? *Pesach* and not
מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot* in themselves? We noted that the מרור *maror* was—the
משנה Mishnah *mishna* gave the שיעור *shiur* of כזית *k'zayit*, which is
questionable whether that was really required when the מרור *maror* was just
an accompaniment to the קרבן פסח korban Pesach. *korban Pesach*. So but
that was the question we raised, and—but we noted at the time
that it didn't mention פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, so maybe it was talking
about nowadays. Let's look at this משנה *mishna* because this משנה *mishna*
now talks about the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban Pesach*. And it
says אין מבשלין Ein mebashlin. את הפסח *ein mevashelin et hapesach*. You
don't cook the פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, right? The פסח Pesach *Pesach* has
to be צלי אש tzeli esh. *tzli esh*, roasted. אל תאכלו ממנו
נא ובשל מבושל במים al tochlu mimenu na u'vashal mevushal b'mayim *Al
tochlu mimenu na uvashel mevushal bamayim*, says the תורה Torah *Torah*. Do
not eat from it raw or quasi-cooked, not fully cooked, or cooked
with a liquid. So the משנה *mishna* says אין מבשלין את הפסח
*ein mevashelin et hapesach*. You can't cook it לא במשקין *lo bemashkin*.
Not only are you not allowed to cook it במים Bamayim. *bemayim*
as the תורה Torah *Torah* says, but you can't use any liquids
ולא במי פירות *velo bemei peirot*, and not with fruit juices. אבל
סכין ומטבילין אותו בהן *Aval sachin umatbilin oto bahen*. Although that's true,
you don't cook it in juices and in liquids, but if it's
roasting on the fire, you can baste it. Okay? So you can
put some like some liquids on it to add some flavor
on the surface level
as it's roasting on the fire. And also, when you eat it,
you can dip it into some liquids. You can use liquids as
a dip, but you can't actually cook it in liquids.
You can't make פסח Pesach *Pesach* stew.
Right, you can't just make
cooked—like you can make boiled chicken, you can't make boiled פסח Pesach
*Pesach*. We'll talk about pan-roasted in a
minute. Okay, now back to חמץ chametz, *chametz* discussions. מי תשמישו של
נחתום *Mei tashmisho shel nachtom*. The... The sort of working water of
the, of the baker, meaning if a baker's baking bread, he's got
a bucket of water near him that he's dipping his hands in,
they didn't have running water regularly to clean his hands between, you
know, one loaf and between like one, one batch and the next.
So that water, ישפכו, you have to spill it out, מפני שהן
מחמיצין, mipnei shehein machmitzin, because it's got little pieces of, you know,
dough in it and it's sitting around, so it's going to become
חמץ. chametz So the organization here is a little wild, to say
the least. What the heck is it doing? First of all, right?
And the next פרק perek is all going to be about חמץ
chametz altogether. So first of all, why two דפים dapim ago or
three דפים dapim ago do we start talking about מצה ומרור matzah
v'maror in the middle of חמץ chametz. discussions? But okay, if we're
going to talk about them, fine. But then we double back to
חמץ chametz. discussions, then we to חמץ chametz discussions, then we talk
about something about eating the פסח, Pesach and then we go back
to חמץ discussions right afterwards. So תוספות Tosafot raises this question. I
have no idea what the answer is. The organization here is a
very, is very strange. The other question of course about the baker
is the issue of, you know, if, if he's dipping his hands
in this water and it's becoming חמץ, how's he allowed to do
that over פסח? Pesach. Meaning forget about the spilling it out, right?
Why is he allowed, why's he allowed to allow that to let
that happen, you know, if he's baking מצות matzot on פסח, Pesach.
he's allowing there to be חמץ on פסח. Pesach So that's not
clear either. So we will talk about all of this, but the
organization issues of the משניות mishnayot is a real question.
So, so we don't like the thought that this משנה is all
about liquids and it's A-B-A?
You mean, yeah, but about liquids and then introducing, I mean, we
said sections, every section. Yes, I do understand, but it just seems
to me that going about a totally different issue about liquids of
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you're right. I mean, it's about, that
is true. It's about mixing stuff with some type of a liquid,
you know, flour with a liquid, פסח Pesach with a liquid, right?
Or, you know, I mean, or at least drying, you know, using
liquids to wash your hands. But it does still, look, you might
be absolutely correct that that's it, but it still seems very strange
that it is that the overarching issue of a discussion of חמץ
in order to get maybe a third thing about a liquid, we
ran to how you eat the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach Okay? There seems to be, it would seem
to me, first of all, if you wanted a third thing about
a liquid, we had the previous משנה about the bran and the
liquid for the, you know, for the chickens and whatnot. Maybe that
was also three. It actually was three. It was the bran, the
woman with the, to at the bathhouse, and the man chewing or
the other person chewing it and putting it on his wound. So
you are right. It's a good point that there are three things
about liquids with flour and grain. It still seems quite strange about
why, why, you know, a few דפים dapim ago we had two
separate משניות mishnayot all about מצה ומרור matzah v'maror and why here
we have to run to a case about the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach, So maybe what you're, what you've said though is a partial
answer. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב כהנא,
Amar Rav Kahana, מחלוקת לתוך החרדל. machloket l'toch hachardal. That issue about
whether if you went ahead and mixed the flour, can you eat
it or do you have to destroy it is about, you know,
is about the mustard. אבל לתוך החרוסת, Aval l'toch hacharoset, but if
it's into this חרוסת charoset? dip, דברי הכל ישרף מיד, divrei hakol
yisaref miyad, then it has to be burnt immediately. רש"י says the
difference is is that the mustard is just more pungent, so that
will maybe more retard the, the, the process of of it becoming
חמץ. And therefore there might be an opinion that you can eat
it before it becomes חמץ. But the, but by this חרוסת charoset?
dip, he's claiming everybody would say you have to burn it, you
cannot eat it, even immediately. ותניא נמי הכי, V'tanya nami hachi, we've
taught similarly in a ברייתא, braita, אין נותנין קמח לתוך החרוסת, ein
notnin kemach l'toch hacharoset, you don't put flour into the חרוסת, charoset?
ואם נתן ישרף מיד, v'im natan yisaref miyad, and if you do
you have to burn immediately. לתוך החרדל, L'toch hachardal, if however you
put it into mustard, that's where we have a debate. ר' מאיר
אומר ישרף מיד, Rabbi Meir omer yisaref miyad, you burn it, וחכמים
אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, and the sages say, in that case, יאכל מיד,
you can eat it. So although the משנה is not clear, the
משנה says according to the חכמים chachamim you can eat it, he
is saying, רב כהנא Rav Kahana is saying with a backup of
a ברייתא, braita, that the חכמים chachamim would only allow that in
the mustard case. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהודה אמר רב נחמן
אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehuda amar Rav Nachman amar
Shmuel, הלכה כחכמים, halacha k'chachamim, and we rule like the חכמים chachamim
that at least in the mustard case you can eat it if
you did it, as long as you eat it immediately.
אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרב הונא בריה דרב יהודה, Amar
lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak l'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehuda, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said to
רב הונא בריה דרב יהודה, Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehuda, the one
who said this tradition ultimately in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, אחרוסת
קאמר מר? acharoset ka'amar mar? When you're saying it's, we rule like
the חכמים chachamim it's permissible, are you saying even by the חרוסת?
Do you think the חכמים chachamim would allow it even like, even
on the חרוסת? או אחרדל קאמר מר? o achardal ka'amar mar? Or
are you saying like רב כהנא Rav Kahana that even when the
חכמים chachamim allowed it, they only allowed it with the mustard? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, למאי נפקא מינה? l'mai nafka mina? He said, למאי
נפקא מינה l'mai nafka mina in the sense of what difference would
it make, what הלכה halacha difference would it make, are you allowed
to do it by the חרוסת? But למאי נפקא מינה l'mai nafka
mina as a way of saying like, why should there be a
difference? Right? Of course... So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says to דרב
כהנא *d'Rav Kahana*, no, because of רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*, רב כהנא
*Rav Kahana* sees that there is a difference, דאמר רב כהנא *d'Amar
Rav Kahana*, מחלוקת לתוך חרדל *machlokes betoch chardal*, that even when the
חכמים *Chachamim* allowed it, when there was a debate it was only
by the mustard, אבל לתוך חרוסת *aval betoch charoset*, by the חרוסת
*charoset*, דברי הכל ישרף מיד *divrei hakol yisaref miyad*, everybody would agree
that the חרוסת *charoset* is a bigger issue and has to be
burned immediately.
Is it a- is it strange to be talking about burning a
liquid?
No, it's not- oh because- is mustard a liquid? חרוסת *charoset*. חרוסת
*charoset*, it's a dip. I know, but is that- yeah, I hear
your point. It's not like- it just struck me right away. It's
thicker. It's thicker, yeah, although pouring it out you have to- apples
is really thick.
Paula's חרוסת *charoset*. Yeah, I bet it is a
quest- very, very thick.
I don't know, it's a- I just- it struck me
as an interesting thing to say burn the pudding.
I hear the point. I hear the point. Okay, anyway, so it
says- so he said so anyway maybe so is there a difference?
On פסח Pesach *Pesach*, right?
On פסח pesach *Pesach*.
In the middle of
פסח pesach *Pesach* you- correct.
Get rid of it. Right. Well, yeah, and you didn't have flush
toilets.
Yeah, but right, exactly. But it could have said put it לימה
המלח *le-Yam Hamelach* or לתוך הנהר *betoch hanahar* or something. They could
have said put it, you know, put it into some, you know,
some river. Anyway, it's okay, I hear. Anyway, but yes, we are
talking on פסח pesach *Pesach* and that's why the question is that
can you eat it before it becomes חמץ *chametz*. So anyway, אמר
ליה *amar lei*, so he said do you make the same- you
know, would you say it even about the- even about the חרוסת
*charoset*? אמר ליה לא שמיע לי *amar lei lo shamia li*. He
said, I haven't heard that teaching of רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* about
a distinction between mustard and חרוסת *charoset*. And now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has a lovely line which comes up in number- כלומר *klomar*,
what he meant by I didn't hear it means לא סבירא ליה
*lo sevira lei*. It means I don't buy it. Okay,
so- tough guess whether I know that he said it or not,
it means like yeah, I don't hear that distinction. Okay, so anyway
he felt it was all the same and we rule like the
חכמים *Chachamim* and even by the חרוסת *charoset*. Okay. אמר רב אשי
כוותיה דרב כהנא מסתברא *Amar Rav Ashi kevastei de-Rav Kahana mistavra*. רב
אשי *Rav Ashi* says, you know what, רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*'s distinction
of mustard and חרוסת *charoset* makes sense. Why? דאמר שמואל *de-amar Shmuel*,
since שמואל *Shmuel* says אין הלכה כרבי יוסי *ein halacha ke-Rabbi Yosi*,
that we don't rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yosi*. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi? *Rabbi Yosi* said yesterday that if you went ahead
and did this, you know, put the- to remove the bran, you
put these- you know, the- barley into water to- you know, remove
the husks and the bran and then they started, you know, blowing
up and cracking, you just throw it into vinegar and the vinegar
prevents fermentation. So, and שמואל *Shmuel* said that we don't rule like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi*, we don't rule like the vinegar
prevents fermentation. Okay, and this teaching that we rule like the חכמים
*Chachamim* is following שמואל *Shmuel*. So, אין הלכה כרבי יוסי *ein halacha
ke-Rabbi Yosi*, מאי לאו lav. *mai lav*, does that not mean צמותי
הוא דלא צמית *tzimutei hu de-lo tzamit*, that if we reject רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* that vinegar prevents fermentation, we're saying that
A, it does not retard, it does not literally shrivel the thing,
does not retard the fermentation, החמויי מחמי *hachmei machme*, and actually it
does the opposite, it serves like a liquid and causes fermentation. So
if שמואל *Shmuel* says we don't rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi.
*Rabbi Yosi* about the vinegar, presumably vinegar causes fermentation. So therefore the
vinegar in the- in the חרוסת *charoset* would be a real problem
and would cause fermentation and you would not be able to eat
it, you'd have to be concerned that it became חמץ *chametz* right
away. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא *lo*, maybe not, דילמא
לא מצמת צמית ולא החמויי מחמי *dilma lo matzmit tzamit velo hachmei
machme*. Maybe it doesn't stop fermentation, but it also doesn't hasten fermentation.
So just because there is vinegar in the- of course as far
as I know there's vinegar in- in mustard as well, but okay,
just because the- the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying that there's vinegar in
this חרוסת *charoset* dip doesn't mean that it ferments faster than the
mustard. So this argument that the חרוסת *charoset* is a bigger problem
than the mustard is not necessarily clear. Even if- even if the
vinegar component doesn't help, it doesn't necessarily hurt. All right, so those
are the two cases of the must- of the mustard and the
חרוסת *charoset* where we say if you've added the flour, it will
ferment, can you eat it before it ferments? Maybe only the mustard,
not the vinegar, and not the- not the what- חרוסת *charoset*.
Why don't they ask a woman? They're the people who probably make
it.
Well, I think the question of does it ferment, you know, if
you're dealing with dough, you can see, you know, is it- is
it expanding, are there cracks in the dough? When you're dealing with
the grains, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also said you look at the
grains, are there cracks in the grain? Is it absorbing the water?
Here, if you're looking at mustard, which has some flour added to
it, or vegetable soup with flour added to it, how do you
see whether it's fermented or not, right? So I think that's the
issue. But maybe you say well if you do it- if you
eat it immediately, but I don't think this was as visible to
identify what had happened.
Yeah, I understand that completely, so it's more of an abstract or
scientific discussion rather than realia. But who's making all these things...
I don't know, it is true that before we speak, well, we
have spoken before about אשה, you know about, we have mentioned women
specifically in some of these cases, which I assume like reflects certain
realities about women doing it. I think specifically right when we said
when a woman is kneading the dough and so on, but some
of these I don't know. You know I do think that I
do think it's generally assumed that the women did all the cooking
and the baking and so on, yes. Although we do have bakers,
נחתומים, nakhtomim, right?
Bakers are men, that's true. But that's I think maybe professionally. I
don't think that the man of the house and at the domestic
thing was doing the baking, you know, but anyway, yes.
Rebbe's maidservant, who's never named as far as I know, often gets
quoted on various things.
Yeah, we're not talking about women being quoted, we're talking about whether
we have evidence about who's like, you know, about who's actually doing
the baking.
It's really difficult to get in and take sounds
out.
Right. Yeah, there is a famous גמרא Gemara later on about לחם
עוני, Lechem Oni, which is the גמרא Gemara in קט"ז ע"א Kuf
Tet Zayin Amud Alef says: מה דרכו של עני הוא מסיק ואשתו
אופה. Ma darko shel ani hu masik v'ishto ofeh. The same way
a poor person, the husband is lighting the fire and the wife
is baking because they don't want to waste the fuel. But presumably
if you're a rich house and you don't mind wasting the fuel,
maybe the servants are doing it or maybe the woman is doing
it all. But definitely an assumption that, you know, again, but as
we see in terms of professionally, there were male bakers, men bakers.
Anyway, moving on, so now we get to eating the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach and again, we're going to have like four פרקים prakim
devoted to the bringing of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach. but here,
way before that, we're talking about the prohibition of eating a פסח
Pesach, that is not roasted but that is cooked or that is
raw. So let's take a look. And although the תורה Torah says
cooked in water, the משנה says cooked in any juices. אין מבשלין.
You don't cook a פסח Pesach in juices.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. במים. Bamayim. In water, right? It says אל
תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבשל במים. Al tochlu mimenu na u'vashel mebushal
bamayim. Now I should say the תורה's Torah prohibition is about eating
it, right? Not about cooking it. Okay, if I went and cooked
it and didn't eat it, okay, it might be other problems that
now the פסח is not usable and the problem of like, you
know, making a קרבן korban not edible, but it is the prohibition
of the תורה Torah is a prohibition of eating. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. במים. bamayim, In water. Don't ובשל מבשל במים. u'vashel mebushal bamayim.
אין לי אלא במים. Ein li ela bamayim. I only know that
it's a problem if it was cooked in water. שאר משקין מנין?
She'ar mashkin minayin? How do I know if it was cooked in
other liquids? אמרת קל וחומר. Amarta kal vachomer. You make a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה מים שאין מפיגין טעמו. U'mah mayim she'ein mafigin
ta'amo. When you cook it in water, the water doesn't introduce, doesn't
weaken the taste. Now obviously it does weaken the taste in the
sense of something boiled in water doesn't taste as strong as something
that's roasted. But the point is it certainly doesn't mask the taste.
It's not introducing a new taste. אסורין. Asurin. And that's forbidden.
שאר משקין שמפיגין טעמם. She'ar mashkin she'mafigin ta'amam. Other liquids that basically
mask the taste, because you know, if you cook it in apple
juice or whatever you cook it in, it adds a new taste.
לא כל שכן? Lo kol sheken? How much more so should that
be included? Now that's a little bit interesting because first of all,
you know we normally say אין מזהירין מן הדין. Ein mazhirin min
hadin. You don't use a קל וחומר kal vachomer in order to
include something in a prohibition. Or if you do, it's certainly not
enough to get lashes. And here it seems like it's equally included
in the prohibition. So every now and then we say, תוספות Tosafot
raised the question, we say not really like a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. It's like, it's a way in which we understand that when
the תורה Torah says במים, bamayim the תורה's Torah talking about like
לשון בני אדם. lashon bnei adam. Like it's talking about like a
paradigmatic case, but that you know, it's a way of understanding that
it's the תורה's Torah being a little לאו דווקא. lav davka. It
really is a way of saying any liquid. So we use the
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but we use the קל וחומר kal vachomer
to say במים bamayim, doesn't really mean במים, bamayim. it really means
in any liquid. But the other interesting thing about the קל וחומר
kal vachomer in addition to the technical question of אין מזהירין עונשין
מן הדין, ein mazhirin onshin min hadin, is that to make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer assumes that we understand the reason why it's
prohibited, right? The reason it's prohibited is because it affects the taste.
Maybe there's another reason why it's prohibited. Maybe it's prohibited because I
don't know, because water symbolizes an ingredient of חמץ and it wouldn't
be true by מי פירות. mei peirot. I mean I'm just making
it up obviously, but the point is you have to assume that
the reason in order to then make a קל וחומר kal vachomer
to say oh well other liquids certainly because they affect the taste.
Anyway, but that's what the גמרא Gemara does and therefore it includes
other liquids.
כל הקרבנות Kol hakorbanot are צלי, tzali, correct?
No, you can the כהנים, Kohanim, I mean what you put on
the on the on the you know, on the מזבח mizbe'ach is
צלי, tzali, but that's only an עולה olah you put the meat
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. When the כהנים Kohanim eat the meat, they
can eat it however they want to eat it, right?
The sons of עלי Eli with the dipping your forks into the
boiling pots.
Right, exactly. The תורה talks about about the pot that you cook
the חטאת chatas in, right? So yeah, you would you would cook
that.
המשניות Hamishnayot in זבחים. Zevachim.
Yeah. Okay. So רבי אומר Rebbi omer. במים. Rebbe does says a
different דרשה drasha rather than the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It says
cooked in water. אין לי אלא מים. Ein li ela mayim. I
only know water. שאר משקין מנין? She'ar mashkin minayin? How about other
liquids?
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ובשל מבשל. u'vashel mebushal. What's the difference between
them? Is there any difference between whether you learn it out from
the double language or you learn it out from the קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? The גמרא Gemara says איכא בינייהו צלי קדרה. ika beinaihu
tzeli kedaura. The difference is pan-roasted, right? Pan-roasted is you're not introducing
any liquid, even water. It's directly by the fire, but then the
juices run off and they sit in the pan and it cooks
in its own juices. Okay, as opposed to a roasting where the
juices run off and they hit the ground.
Okay, so what's the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? So if you make
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, a קל וחומר kal vachomer would only
be for external juices. Don't cook it with water and don't cook
it with any other type of external liquid. Okay, but pan-roasting you
wouldn't get in the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Where if it's ובשל
מבושל, uvashel mevushal, that's not a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, that's saying
anything that affects cooking. So even cooking in its own juices is
a type of a cooking. Okay, so that is the גמרא Gemara
says the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Now תוספות Tosafot points out don't
misunderstand this that according to the קל וחומר kal vachomer that you
would actually be allowed to do a pan-roasted פסח. I mean, we
have never heard of saying you could do a pan-roasted פסח. So
we're going to see later in the גמרא Gemara. that the גמרא
Gemara actually says the end of the פסוק pasuk is כי אם
צלי אש, ki im tzeli esh, right? It only can be fire-roasted.
So כי אם צלי אש ki im tzeli esh means anything that's
not fire-roasted doesn't doesn't is not okay. So even pan-roasted does not
fit into the category of צלי אש. tzeli esh, Okay, so it
would still not be allowed because of that. But that might be
like a positive מצוה. It wouldn't but the argument here is that
whether it's included in the negative prohibition of ובשל מבושל במים, uvashel
mevushal bamayim, that might if you focused on your קל וחומר kal
vachomer that wouldn't include pan-roasting. If you focused on the double language,
then that ובשל מבושל uvashel mevushal would include pan-roasting. But again, either
way, says תוספות, Tosafot, pan-roasting is not צלי אש, tzeli esh which
the תורה insists insists at the end of the פסוק. pasuk.
Yeah, a great core note here is that Rambam rules in accordance
with Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, so you even violate a negative commandment.
Okay, there you go.
You'd need a big pan.
To do, yeah.
To cook the whole animal.
That's true. That's true. Okay, ולרבנן, u'lerabbanan, האי ובשל מבושל מאי עבדי
ליה? hai uvashel mevushal mai avdi lei? So the rabbis, what do
they do with the language of ובשל מבושל uvashel mevushal since they
don't need it to include other juices? So מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaye
lei l'chidatanya, to teach you what we taught in the ברייתא. braita.
בשלו ואחר כך צלאו, bishlo v'achar kach tzla'o, let's say you first
cooked it and then you roasted it, right? או, sort of like
we had something earlier a little bit earlier similar before about like
about first making a dough like first doing it, you know, in
a in a pot and then doing it in an oven. Anyway,
if you cooked the פסח and then you roasted it, right? And
there there was a question of is it still bread or what
not. Anyway, או שצלאו ואחר כך בשלו, o shetzla'o v'achar kach bishlo,
or if you roasted it and then cooked it, חייב. chayav. Either
way you transgress because either way it's an aspect of בישול bishul
even though there's also an aspect of צלי. tzeli. So ובשל מבושל
uvashel mevushal means even if it's not all only cooked, even if
it's cooked and roasted, it's still a problem.
Okay, and I think you see ולרבנן, u'lerabbanan, מאי ובשל מבושל? mai
uvashel mevushal? What do the רבנן rabbanan need? But the מיבעי ליה
mibaye lei is singular.
Ah, מיבעי ליה mibaye lei refers back to
the פסוק, pasuk, not to
the who needs
the teaching. Exactly. Okay. So
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, בשלמא, bishlama, let's think about
that. בשלמא
בשלו ואחר כך
צלאו חייב, bishlama bishlo v'achar kach tzla'o chayav, that I get,
דהא בשליה בשליה. deha bashlei bashlei. You started by cooking it, so
that defines its identity. It's now cooked, so roasting it afterwards doesn't,
you know, get it out of the status of having been cooked.
אלא צלאו ואחר כך בשלו, ela tzla'o v'achar kach bishlo, but if
you first roasted it, הא צלי אש הוא. ha tzeli esh hu.
Maybe the fact that it was originally cooked by roasting should stamp
its identity as roasted by the fire and the cooking afterwards should
not change that. Maybe it should be still considered צלי אש tzli
esh even if it was cooked afterwards. So אמר רב כהנא, amar
Rav Kahana, הא מני רבי יוסי היא. ha mani Rabbi Yosi hi.
This idea that if you did something after it changes its identity,
that follows רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, by not the פסח but by
מצה, matzah a similar discussion. What's this רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi דתניא,
detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. braita. אין
יוצאין ברקיק השרוי, Ein yotzin berakik hashurui, you can fulfill your obligation
of מצה matzah if you take like a wafer and you submerge
it in water and you soak it in water, so it gets
very waterlogged. Nevertheless, it was originally baked, right? That's a real געבראכטס.
Gebraks. Originally baked, that's okay to use for מצה. matzah. And number
two, ובמבושל, uvimvushal, or if you took a מצה matzah, that was
baked and afterwards you cooked your מצה. matzah Okay, so you took
your baked מצה, matzah, you put it in some boiling water, or
let's say you put it in your pot of chicken soup and
you baked it with the chicken soup,
you know. You made your מצה matzah balls, right? And you cooked
them in your chicken soup. You can fulfill your obligation of מצה
matzah, with that because it was originally baked, שלא נימוח, shelo nimoach,
as long as it hasn't dissolved. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir,
that's what רבי Rebbe מאיר says. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer,
רבי יוסי says, יוצאין ברקיק השרוי. yotzin b'rakik hashuruy. I agree with
you when you just, you know, waterlog it. You haven't really done
another action of cooking it. Then it's still considered מצה. matzah אבל
לא במבושל, aval lo b'mevushal, אף על פי שלא נימוח, af al
pi shelo nimoach, but not if it's been baked, if it's been
cooked, even if it hasn't dissolved. Now why not? So if I
ask you why not, you would say, oh by מצה, matzah if
it's been cooked, you know, maybe it's just because then it stops
being like לחם עוני, lechem oni, right? We have all of these
other criteria by מצה matzah about the way it tastes being significant.
This גמרא gemara does not assume that it's an issue of לחם
עוני, lechem oni, then it would be irrelevant to the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach discussion. This גמרא gemara assumes that it's a formal question
of if you do a second act of, you know, baking or
cooking or whatever, does that also change its, does that change its
identity? So that רבי יוסי who says you can't bake מצה, excuse
me, you can't cook מצה after baking it, would say, well once
you've cooked it it's no longer לחם. lechem. לחם lechem is defined
as something baked, and this is now also something cooked, so cooked
stops being לחם. lechem. Ah, so he says the new, a new
label can attach to it even after it's been, you know, one
process has been done. So that's true also by the קרבן פסח,
korban pesach. even though it's already צלי, tzali, if you cook it
after it's צלי, tzali, now it has a new label of being
cooked and not just a label of being roasted. That's רבי יוסי.
So that's what, so that's how the גמרא gemara makes this comparison.
I need to say that this leads to a very important discussion
or relevant discussion by שבת, Shabbat, because we normally have a principle
of אין בישול אחר בישול, ein bishul achar bishul, right? Which is
why if I go ahead and I, you know, cook my chicken
before שבת, Shabbat, I can go ahead and put it on the
fire on שבת Shabbat again, a בלעך blech or whatever, warming plate,
I won't deal with the rabbinic concerns, even if it gets boiling
hot, why? Because it's already cooked, so I can't cook it again,
אין בישול אחר בישול. ein bishul achar bishul. Well, comes along the
יראים Yereim and he says, yes, but you know what you can't
do? You can't go ahead and take your חלה challah and put
it into your boiling hot chicken soup. Why not? Because that's not
בישול אחר בישול, bishul achar bishul, that is בישול אחר אפייה. bishul
achar afiyah. And when it's a different thing, then it changes the
status and that is halachically problematic. And he brings his proof from
this גמרא. gemara You see that according to רבי יוסי, right? Even
though it was already baked the מצה, if you cook it afterwards
it changes the status. And even though the קרבן פסח korban pesach,
was already roasted, if you cook it afterwards it changes the status.
So his argument is that change of status would also be significant
for הלכות שבת. hilchot Shabbat. And that's, and he, so that is
a very relevant הלכות שבת hilchot Shabbat criteria.
You can learn that from ברכות Berachot too, from the הלכות halachot
of ברכות Berachot as well, right?
That the ברכה beracha changes.
You have a loaf of bread and you make bread pudding out
of it. Right, you have a המוציא Hamotzi necessarily.
Right, right, but again that's, some of that is true even without
cooking and so therefore it wouldn't be as relevant because nobody would
say if you take a loaf of bread and you, you know,
chop it up and make pudding or whatever, that on שבת Shabbat
you've transgressed the prohibition of cooking. So, you know, that's the question,
like which of these cases is a model to other cases and
which of them you could say it's following its own הלכות halachot
but not necessarily a more global concept. Okay, yes.
Yeah, I was actually taught that I should be careful that any
soup I have on my, in front of me when I'm eating
it should be a כלי שלישי kli shlishi so I can put
מצה in it.
Right, because the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch is מחמיר machmir for that
position of the יראים. Yereim.
And then the, but the point is also, but why is it
an issue anyway? Your soup bowl is a כלי שני kli sheni
and we just learned yesterday the משנה that a כלי שני kli
sheni is not a problem in הלכות שבת. hilchot Shabbat. So then
the יראים Yereim comes along and he says another חומרא chumra of
the יראים Yereim which is if it's, some things cook even in
a כלי שני. kli sheni. So we sort of have all of
the חומרא, chumra, a lot of חומרות chumrot of the יראים. Yereim.
היראים, HaYereim, by the way, I should say was רבי אליעזר ממיץ,
Rabbi Eliezer MiMetz, a תלמיד talmid of רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. And
he, he did a book called היראים HaYereim which is a book
of מצוות mitzvot like listing the מצוות and the הלכות halachot about
them, but about a third of the entire work is devoted to
הלכות שבת. hilchot Shabbat. And he has a good number of חומרות.
chumrot. So anyway.
חסידי אשכנז, Chassidei Ashkenaz, no?
No, later. He was a תלמיד talmid of רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
I don't think so, I think you're thinking about רבי יהודה החסיד
Rabbi Yehuda HeChassid maybe.
Yeah, well so I thought it was all the same אסכולה.
askola. You might be right, you
might
be right, you might be right, I don't know. Okay, let's go
on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's,
so it's based on that רבי יוסי and that therefore would be
a problem even by the קרבן פסח. korban pesach So the גמרא
Gemara says, עולא אמר, Ulla amar, אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, afilu teima
Rabbi Meir, even רבי מאיר who says that by מצה it's not,
that by מצה it's not an issue, would say that by קרבן
korban פסח it is an issue. Why? שאני התם, shani hatam, here
פסח is different, דאמר קרא, de'amar kra, ובשל מבושל, u'vashel mevushal, מכל
מקום, mikol makom, because that's exactly what the double language is telling
you. That even if in some global way in all other areas,
if you do a second process... it doesn't change the status, but
by פסח the double language of ובשל מבשל u-bashal mevushal says even
if the בישול bishul is a second act that's done to it,
that's enough to taint it and to say that it cannot be
eaten as a קרבן פסח. Okay, so that was the issue of
בישול אחר צלי bishul achar tzli or בישול אחר אפייה. bishul achar
afiyah. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: יכול צלאו כל צרכו
יהא חייב, yachol tzala'o kol tzorko yehei chayav,
maybe if you roasted it completely you'd be חייב? chayav? Now what
does that mean? Why should if you roasted it completely? So the
גמרא Gemara is going to say it means basically maybe if you
charred it, maybe if you roasted it to the point of it
turning it almost into a piece of like you know into burnt,
maybe
you that would also not be considered צלי אש tzli esh. because
it would be charred. תלמוד לומר אל תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבשל
במים, talmud lomar al tochlu mimenu na u-vashal mevushal ba-mayim, don't eat
from it raw or cooked in water. נא ובשל אמרתי לך na
u-vashal amarti lach I only told you those things ולא שצלאו כל
צרכו, ve-lo she-tzala'o kol tzorko, not if you completely roasted it, that
you don't transgress. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what does that mean? אמר
רב אשי דשויה חרוכא, amar rav ashi de-shavei charucha, you basically turned
it into a piece of charcoal, which is a little bit funny,
so maybe you don't transgress the prohibition of אל תאכלו ממנו נא,
al tochlu mimenu na, but have you been יוצא yotzei your מצוות
קרבן פסח? mitzvat korban pesach? Presumably not, I don't know if you
could call that אכילת פסח, achilat pesach, you know it's not דרך
אכילה derech achilah to eat it like that. Okay, but anyway.
Is that would it be
would it be a פיגול? pigul? No, the פיגול pigul has to
do with your מחשבה, machshavah, you know. Okay, anyway so okay but
we did exclude that. Now, it's a little funny we needed to
exclude that because right now we haven't included anything other than various
forms of cooking. But this is leading up to the fact that
the גמרא Gemara is going to say that we include anything that
is not does not satisfy צלי אש. tzli esh, So not just
cooked, not just raw, anything that doesn't satisfy צלי אש, tzli esh,
okay? So therefore but what but if it's overly roasted, that would
not be included in the prohibition. So תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we
taught: יכול אכל כזית חי יהא חייב, yachol achal kezayit chai yehei
chayav, maybe if it's completely raw, you it was like never touched
any form of heat, completely raw you'd transgress? Okay. תלמוד לומר אל
תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבשל. talmud lomar al tochlu mimenu na u-vashal
mevushal. נא, na, which we're going to say means like, you know
like, undercooked or or you know or or cooked. נא ובשל אמרתי
לך, na u-vashal amarti lach, that's what I said to you ולא
חי, ve-lo chai, not completely raw. So ironically again, whether you're יוצא
yotzei the מצוות קרבן פסח, mitzvat korban pesach, presumably not, it's still
not צלי אש, tzli esh? but did you transgress נא ובשל מבשל?
na u-vashal mevushal? No, some things aren't in that פסוק. pasuk. Completely
raw is not, over-roasted is not, that's not in those categories. Okay.
נא ובשל אמרתי לך ולא חי. na u-vashal amarti lach ve-lo chai.
Raw is not included. יכול יהא מותר? yachol yehei mutar? Now we
get to this idea. There's two halves of the פסוק: pasuk: נא
ובשל מבשל na u-vashal mevushal and the other half is כי אם
צלי אש. ki im tzli esh. Okay, so נא ובשל מבשל na
u-vashal mevushal doesn't include overly roasted, doesn't include raw, maybe doesn't include
pan roasted. But how about the end of the פסוק, pasuk, that
it has to be צלי אש? tzli esh. So יכול יהא מותר?
yachol yehei mutar? תלמוד לומר כי אם צלי אש. talmud lomar ki
im tzli esh. No, it might not be the first half of
נא ובשל, na u-vashal, but you still have the problem of it's
not צלי אש. tzeli eish. היכי דמי נא? heichi dami na? Now
what is this נא na that's meant by the פסוק pasuk that
is not raw? So אמר רב אמר רב כדאמרי פרסאי amar rav
amar rav ke-damrei parsa'ei like the Persians say, אברנים. avarnim. That was
the way they referred to this cooked meat, which basically means like,
you know, rare, or something, like you know very you know it's
roasted but it's mostly it's still very undercooked. So we might I
don't know we might say rare might be what's being described. אמר
רב חסדא המבשל בחמי טבריה, amar rav chisda ha-mevashel be-chamei tveryah,
let's say you cooked the קרבן פסח, forgetting the liquid you used,
you did not use the heat of a fire, you you did
it with the hot waters of Tiberias, right where it came from
underground, you know the heat came from the underground. Okay, so בשבת
פטור. be-shabbat patur. In שבת shabbat you're exempt. By שבת shabbat something
it's only considered cooking if it uses an actual heat of a
fire. Now, פסח שבישלו בחמי טבריה, pesach she-bishlo be-chamei tveryah, however by
the פסח if you cooked it in חמי טבריה, chamei tveryah, חייב,
chayav, you transgress. So it is considered ובשל מבשל. u-bashal mevushal. So
the גמרא Gemara says what's the difference? מאי שנא בשבת דלא? mai
shna be-shabbat de-la? Why by שבת shabbat is it not you don't
transgress? דתולדות אש בעינן, de-toldot esh ba'inan, you need something that is
a fire or a or a descendant of fire. What descendant of
fire means is is that if you let's say heat up, the
גמרא Gemara has an example, sand. If you heat it up in
a fire and then you put an egg in the sand and
the egg cooks by the heat of the sand, that's cooking in
תולדות אש, toldot esh, or an easier example, you heat up your
hot water on fire, you remove it from the fire, and then
you put your eggs or whatever into the hot water not directly
on the fire, so it's cooking in the water, it's not cooking
directly over the fire. But the water was heated by the fire.
So by שבת shabbat it's only considered cooking if it's fire or
a or a derivation of fire. Not if it's heated through something
else.
דתולדות אש בעינן וליכא, de-toldot esh ba'inan ve-leika, and you don't have
it by this case of חמי טבריה. chamei tveryah. פסח נמי לאו
תולדות אש הוא. pesach nami lav toldot esh hu. So by פסח
it should be the same definition of what defines cooking. So why
is it different?
You put the קרבן פסח in the חמי טבריה, chamei tveryah,
in the חמי טבריה, chamei tveryah, and the question
is why should that be, in other words you have the liquid
Right.
So you mean why don't you just say there's a problem of
כעין צלי? ke'ein tzlui? No, no, no, in it, in it. But
the problem... so you're saying why is it not a problem of
כעין צלי? ke'ein tzlui? Okay, maybe, maybe, so that but he's saying
forget right, but he's saying at least it shouldn't be in the
בשל מבושל bashal mevushal category because we normally define מבושל mevushal as
cooked with fire. Okay, if you tell me it's not צלי tzlui
fine, but it shouldn't be בשל מבושל. bashal mevushal.
So there's a hermeneutic question.
Yeah. Right, or or as we're going to see if it's only
in the end of the פסוק pasuk of כי אם צלי ki
im tzlui might be that that's an עשה, aseh, it might be
that that's you don't get מלקות malkus for it. Okay, so we're
not saying it's מותר, muttar, but we're just we are saying why
are you saying...
Is it so
hot חמי טבריה?
chamai tverya? Yeah. And in order to cook something
on שבת, Shabbos, you've got to walk into it on שבת. Shabbos.
How could you...
That's only rabbinic, or you could stand outside and drop it in.
Anyway, but that's a... Oh right, but that's a... I don't know,
that's like a different question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
so אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava says and this gets
what is what Dov was saying, Shhh, come on, מאי חייב, mai
chaya, what does it mean you transgressed? דקא עבר משום צלי. d'ka
avar mishum tzlui. Yes, okay, you wouldn't be בשל מבושל. bashal mevushal.
בישול bishul is with fire, but what we're saying is you still
would have transgressed or not fulfilled כי אם צלי ki im tzlui
because it's still not considered to be roasted. But it's okay, it's
not cooked technically, but it's also not roasted. Now I do want
to say that the גמרא Gemara could have had another answer. The
גמרא Gemara could have said that by שבת Shabbos it what matters
more is the process and the act. So therefore if we define
an act of cooking, we might say only certain types of things
are defined as cooking, a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, fire and so
on. But by the פסח, we're interested in the result, the product,
do you consider the product to be a cooked product? So even
if the way it was done was a very unusual way that
you used חמי טבריה, chamai tverya, you did it by the sun,
whatever you did, maybe that wasn't a process of cooking, but we
might still be able to call the end thing having been cooked.
So the גמרא Gemara, does not make that distinction. The גמרא Gemara,
says I'll concede it's not cooked, but it's certainly not צלי. tzlui.
רב חייא בריה דרב נחמן מתני לה להא דרב חסדא בהדיא. Rav
Chiya brei d'Rav Nasman masni lah l'ha d'Rav Chisda behedya. רב חייא
Rav Chiya the son of רב נחמן Rav Nasman teaches that explicitly
in this teaching of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר רב חסדא המבשל
בחמי טבריה בשבת פטור, amar Rav Chisda hamvashel b'chamai tverya b'Shabbos patur,
if you cook in חמי טבריה chamai tverya on שבת Shabbos you're
exempt. ופסח שבישלו בחמי טבריה u'Pesach she'bishlo b'chamai tverya if you did
it with the פסח חייב, chayav, you transgressed, but what do you
transgress? שעבר משום צלי. she'avar mishum tzlui. The end of the פסוק.
pasuk. You did... so it's not בשל מבושל bashal mevushal but it
is the problem of כי אם צלי. ki im tzlui. Now again,
this question of is that still a negative prohibition? Because we've already
listed a couple of things that are not in the first half
of the פסוק. pasuk. You know,
if it's completely נא, na, that's not in the first half of
the פסוק. pasuk. If it's turned into a piece of charcoal, that's
not the first half of the פסוק, pasuk, but it seems like
it should still at least be the second half of the פסוק
pasuk of כי אם צלי, ki im tzlui, which is now what
the גמרא is emphasizing that there are many things that fall into
the anything other than roasted category.
Is it peculiar to say that you're עובר over a positive מצווה...
mitzvah...
So that is the question. Is it a positive מצווה? mitzvah? And
the גמרא here is assuming, and this is what the גמרא is
going to move to, the גמרא's assuming that you can read the
end of the פסוק pasuk as...
here when it speaks about transgressing, it's reading the end of the
פסוק pasuk as a negative prohibition. אל תאכלו ממנו כי אם צלי.
al tochlu mimenu ki im tzlui. Don't eat from it, you know,
anything that is not roasted. So that actually would be a negative
prohibition. Okay, the other way of the reading of the פסוק pasuk
is אל תאכלו ממנו נא al tochlu mimenu na ובשל מבושל mevushal,
במים period, כי אם צלי ki im tzlui is how you should
eat it, right? And therefore you read the end of the פסוק
pasuk as a positive מצווה. mitzvah. So תוספות Tosafos says, you know,
that second possibility is never explicit in the גמרא, but תוספות Tosafos
says that's floating around there. The possibility of reading the end of
the פסוק pasuk as a positive. But this question how do you
read כי אם צלי ki im tzlui as connected to the negative
or as a standalone positive מצווה. mitzvah. Okay, אמר רבא, amar Rava,
says
רבא, Rava, אכלו נא, achlo na, and here we're going to see
exactly how seriously some people take the כי אם צלי ki im
tzlui as a negative, if you ate from it raw, or נא,
na, whatever, rare let's say, לוקה שתים, lokeh shtayim, you get two
sets of lashes. Why do you get two sets? One for אל
תאכלו ממנו נא na, and can you guess what the other set
of lashes is for? אל תאכלו ממנו כי אם צלי. al tochlu
mimenu ki im tzlui. That צלי tzlui is an actual negative prohibition
that you would get lashes for. If you ate מבושל, mevushal if
you ate from it cooked, לוקה שתים, lokeh shtayim, you get two
sets of lashes for מבושל mevushel. and for כי אם צלי. ki
im tzlui. נא ומבושל, na u'mevushal,
let's say I don't know, part of your קרבן was, you know,
was rare and the other part was cooked and you did both,
so לוקה שלש, lokeh shalosh, you get three lashes, right? One for
נא, na one for בשל מבושל bashal mevushal and one for כי
אם צלי. ki im tzlui. But basic point is you get lashes
for כי אם צלי. ki im tzlui.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says, אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות.
ein lokin al lav shebechlalos. You don't get lashes for a generic
לאו. lav Don't eat except for roasted. So it doesn't identify the
particular, the particular sort of thing that you, that you can't do.
It's anything other than roasted. That is a generic
umbrella, maybe is the better word, an umbrella prohibition and you don't
get lashes for that. So you don't get lashes for כי אם
צלי אש ki im tzeli eish according to אביי. Abaye. Very important
principle of אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות. ein lokin al lav shebichlalus.
Okay. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some say that according to אביי, Abaye,
תרתי הוא דלא לקי, tarti hu d'lo laki, you don't get two
sets of lashes, חדא מיהא לקי, chada mei'ha laki, you get one
set. Now presumably the one set you're getting is for נא na
and מבושל. Okay, but that doesn't fit with the end of this
line because then it says
איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some say חדא נמי לא לקי, chada nami
lo laki, you don't even get one set of lashes דלא מיחד
לאוי כלאו דחסימה. d'lo miyechad lavei k'lav d'chasimah. It's not a specific
לאו lav. like the prohibition of חסימה. chasimah. What does that mean?
The paradigm for when you get lashes is the prohibition of
muzzling your ox when it threshes because it says לא תחסום שור
בדישו lo sachsom shor b'disho and then it speaks about if somebody
comes to the judges and they find him deserving of lashes ארבעים
יכנו לא יוסיף. arba'im yakenu lo yosif. So we use the prohibition
of muzzling an ox as a very specific prohibition. It's about doing
an action and that serves as a paradigm for what you need
to get lashes. Not passive, it has to be active, it has
to be specific. Now what does it mean you don't get one
set?
I mean if I eat from it נא na, or I eat
בשל מבושל, bashel mevushel, it is a very specific לאו. lav So
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos have a whole discussion what this line
means. I'll tell you what רש״י Rashi says. רש״י Rashi says no,
no, no, אביי Abaye of course would never say that if you
ate בשל מבושל bashel mevushel you wouldn't get lashes. Of course you'd
get lashes. The question is the following: when you say you don't
get lashes על לאו שבכללות, al lav shebichlalus, what happens when that
prohibition comes by itself? Meaning what אביי Abaye might be saying is
the following: if I eat from it בשל מבושל, bashel mevushel, you
can't get me for two things. Oh, we're going to give you
lashes for having eaten cooked and for having eaten it any way
other than roasted. Every way other than roasted is redundant once you're
giving me lashes for not eating from it cooked. It's like why
when you find somebody guilty of murder, you not also find him
guilty of attempted murder? You did attempt murder, right? But no, if
you've actually already done murder, it's not meaningful to also talk about
this more generic, this other type thing. That's because it's preparatory. So
if you're already giving the guy lashes for בשל מבושל, bashel mevushel,
you don't give him lashes for a catch-all of anything other than
צלי אש. But what if he didn't, he ate from it not
בשל מבושל? bashel mevushel? He ate from it for example completely raw.
Not בשל מבושל, bashel mevushel, not נא, na completely raw. Then we
can't give him a specific prohibition, but we can apply the generic
כי אם צלי אש. ki im tzeli eish. So that's the question.
When אביי Abaye says when it comes together with a specific one,
you certainly don't get lashes for it. When it comes by itself,
do you get lashes for it? And argument could be made yes,
nothing else is relevant so we'll give him this generic category. And
another argument could be made no, even when it comes by
itself, an umbrella prohibition that's not about a specific narrowly defined thing,
you would never get lashes even when it stands alone by itself.
That's how רש״י Rashi reads the גמרא, two positions within אביי. Abaye.
Okay, in a similar way, now this is going to רבא אמר.
Rava amar. So רבא Rava says אכל זג, achal zag, if a
it says a נזיר, nazir, he can't eat מחרצנים ועד זג, mechartzanim
v'ad zag, from the skin to the pit. So if he ate
the pit לוקה שתים, lokei shtayim, he gets two lashes, one for
eating the pit and the other from saying מכל אשר יעשה מגפן
היין, mikol asher yei'aseh m'gefen hayayin, another umbrella category, anything that comes
from the vine. So and you have something specific. It says don't
eat the pit. So if he ate the pit, he gets the
specific lashes of pit and the very umbrella lashes of anything that
comes from the vine. חרצן, chartzan, if he ate the skin of
the grapes, לוקה שתים lokei shtayim too because it says מחרצנים mechartzanim
and it also says anything. זג וחרצן, zag v'chartzan, if he ate
the pit and the skin לוקה שלש, lokei shalosh, one for the
pit, one for the skin, and one for the generic.
אביי אמר אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות. Abaye amar ein lokin al
lav shebichlalus. אביי Abaye says no, I'm sorry, if you ate the
pit you only get one lashes. If you ate the skin you
only get one. This generic anything that comes from the vine, you're
not going to also get lashes for that if you're already getting
lashes for the pit or for the skin.
That's the title of the לאו lav in a way. In other
words, that's the לאו שבכללות? lav shebichlalus? No, in other words,
in other words, you don't get מלכות malkus
for violating the name of the general לאו lav, of which you've
done a specific act, and there'll be five different acts that come
under that title. You don't get lashes for the title as well
as the act.
Right, but איכא דאמרי ika d'amri now some say תרתי הוא דלא
לקי, tarti hu d'lo laki, fine, when they come, when there's an
issue of two you don't give him for this because you give
him for the more specific one, you give him for the pit
or for the skin. חדא מיהא לקי, chada mei'ha laki, but if
it came by itself, I'm reading it like רש״י. Rashi. Like you
ate something that wasn't the pit, that wasn't the skin, that was
still some derivative of the vine. According to that, you would get
lashes cause there's nothing else that's more relevant. איכא דאמרי Ikka De-amri
and some say חדא נמי לא לקי. Chada nami lo laki. No,
even if there was nothing else that was more relevant, you would
never get lashes for this generic מכל אשר יצא, mikol asher yeitzei,
דלא מייחד לאו כלאו דחסימה. delo meyached lav kelav de-chasima. It's not
specific, it doesn't really clearly identify a specific thing like the prohibition
of muzzling, and therefore you would never get lashes even by itself.
Okay, so that is the question about looking at the end of
the pasuk of כי תצא. Ki Seitzei. According to both of them,
it's a prohibition, but the question is would you get lashes. But
again, there's another possibility out there that תוספות Tosafot indicates to read
the end of the pasuk as a positive mitzvah, not as a
negative mitzvah. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught. אכלו כזית נא
בעוד יום, Achalo kezayit na be-od yom, let's say you ate the
Korban Pesach, it was prepared the wrong way, but you ate it
on the 14th. You didn't eat it, right? Because you already brought
it on Erev Pesach and you maybe prepared it on Erev Pesach.
Do you transgress only when you eat it the wrong way during
the time of the mitzvah at night? What if you ate it
the wrong way prior to the night? Okay, so אכלו כזית נא
בעוד יום, Achalo kezayit na be-od yom, if you ate it rare
the day before, פטור, patur, you're exempt. כזית נא משחשיכה חייב. Kezayit
na mishechasheicha chayav. But if you ate it that way once it
got dark, you're chayav. So it's only about doing it the wrong
way once the mitzvah begins to apply.
So there's no minhag like we have of not eating matzah 30
days before for the taste of the mitzvah?
About not. It didn't say it was muttar to eat it before
the right time, okay, but that might be a different issue than
the question of have you transgressed the lav. אכלו כזית צלי בעוד
יום, Achalo kezayit tzali be-od yom, similarly, and this almost goes without
saying, if you ate it roasted on the day before,
לא פסל עצמו מבני חבורה. lo pasal atzmo mi-benei chavurah. You did
not sort of, you know,
invalidate yourself for the rest of the group. What does that mean?
I mean, it doesn't have to say if you ate it the
day before you didn't fulfill the mitzvah. We all know the mitzvah
is the 15th. But there's a halakha that is is that you
cannot eat the, you cannot eat
in two different חבורות. chavurot. So if I go ahead and I
start eating my Korban Pesach with you guys, I can't go ahead
and take my Korban Pesach and go ahead and eat it with
another group of people. So let's say Erev Pesach we all couldn't
contain ourselves and we sat down and we all had a little
taste of the Pesach beforehand. So if I, so now do we
say, oh, so now come the night, I can't eat it with
my other group. We don't say that because I did it on
Erev Pesach. So what I did on Erev Pesach was not a
significant eating of the Pesach. It doesn't have the status of eating
of the Pesach, whether to say I've transgressed by doing it if
it was cooked, whether to say that it defines where I've eaten
the Pesach, because that didn't count as eating the Pesach.
Okay. כזית צלי משחשיכה, Kezayit tzali mishechasheicha, but once I've eaten it
and it's been roasted and it's dark, פסל עצמו מבני חבורה, pasal
atzmo mi-benei chavurah, I invalidate myself from going ahead and eating with
another group. Presumably, if I ate it when it was dark but
I ate it בשל מבושל במים, bashel mevushal bamayim, I wouldn't invalidate
myself from another group. I transgressed, but that would not be, that
might not be defined as a group of eating the Pesach to
invalidate me from another group.
Okay, תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we turned another beraita. יכול אכלו
כזית נא בעוד יום יהא חייב, Yachol achalo kezayit na be-od yom
yehei chayav, maybe if you ate it raw on Erev... not raw,
rare Erev Pesach, you would transgress. ודין הוא, Ve-din hu, I could
make an
argument to say you transgress on Erev Pesach.
ומה בשעה שישנו בקומי אכול צלי, Uma besha'ah she-yeshno be-kumei echol tzali,
when you're already allowed to do some things with it like you're
allowed to eat it roasted, ישנו בבל תאכל נא, yeshno be-val tochal
na, you nevertheless are not allowed to eat it
rare. בשעה שאינו בקומי אכול צלי, Besha'ah she-eino be-kumei echol tzali, Erev
Pesach where you're not supposed to be eating the Korban Pesach in
Erev Pesach, so it's even off-limits from the prohibition of
roasted, אינו דין שישנו בבל תאכל נא? eino din she-yeshno be-val tochal
na? So it certainly should be a time when it's more prohibited.
Right, Erev Pesach you can't even eat it roasted, so you should
also be prohibited of eating it rare. או לא, O lo, or
maybe I say no. בשעה שאינו בקומי אכול צלי, Besha'ah she-eino be-kumei
echol tzali, ישנו בבל תאכל נא, yeshno be-val tochal na, maybe they
are the reverse. When it is
a time when it is not you're commanded to eat it roasted,
Erev
Pesach, ישנו בבל תאכל נא, yeshno be-val tochal na, that's the time
only on Erev Pesach
you transgress the prohibition of eating it rare. בשעה שישנו בקומי אכול
צלי, Besha'ah she-yeshno be-kumei echol tzali, and maybe on the night when
you are obligated to eat it roasted, אינו בבל תאכל נא, eino
be-val tochal na, really ironic, maybe you wouldn't transgress. Meaning what it
is doing, both of these sides are assuming that maybe I can
make an argument that Erev Pesach is more prohibited. Because Erev Pesach
you're not even allowed yet to eat it roasted, so maybe Erev
Pesach A, maybe the prohibition of eating it rare and cooked applies
even on Erev Pesach, and then it goes further. Maybe it says
maybe the prohibition applies only on Erev Pesach. Okay. Maybe when the
night comes and you're already commanded... understood and allowed to eat it
roasted, you won't transgress if you eat it otherwise, which is of
course quite ironic. So the Gemara says, so it says, so it
realizes that that sounds like a very strange statement. So it says,
אל תתמה, al titema, don't be so astounded, שהותר מכללו אצל צלי,
shehutar miklalo eitzel tzali, when the night comes, it's being made permitted
to eat it roasted. So maybe that should mean that you don't
transgress even the other prohibitions of rare and cooked etc. תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, so the verse teaches: אל תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבשל
במים כי אם צלי אש. Al tochlu mimenu na uvashel mevushal bamyim
ki im tzli eish. Don't eat rare or cooked, rather roasted. שאין
תלמוד לומר כי אם צלי אש. She'ein talmud lomar ki im tzli
eish. Why does it contrast it to roasted? I mean, that might
be a catchall to tell you other things are off-limits. But the
reason the Pasuk phrases this as a contrast is to tell you,
ומה תלמוד לומר כי אם צלי אש, uma talmud lomar ki im
tzli eish, what's the purpose of this juxtaposition and contrast? לומר לך,
lomar lach, to tell you, בשעה שישנו בקום אכול צלי ישנו בבל
תאכל נא. besha'ah sheyeshno bekum echol tzli yeshno beval tochal na. When
you have the Mitzvah of eating it roasted at the night, that's
when you have the prohibition of eating it rare. בשעה שאינו בקום
אכול צלי, besha'ah she'eino bekum echol tzli, when you don't have that
prohibition, wait, when you don't have that Mitzvah, when it's not yet
the night, אינו בבל תאכל נא, eino beval tochal na, you do
not have the prohibition of eating rare. So this said, I could
have made an argument that the prohibition of eating rare or cooked
applies even the day before, and I could have even gone further
and said it applies only the day before. But the Pasuk is
very clear. The Pasuk says that when you're supposed to eat- you're
supposed to eat it roasted, don't eat it these other ways, so
these prohibitions of don't eat it these other ways only applies at
the time of eating it roasted, only applies at night. Okay, רבי
אומר.
Rebbi omer, But how do we know that women are included in
this time-bound Mitzvah?
So we will get to that, that's a major discussion in the
second half of the Masechet, which deals with Korban Pesach, about women's
obligation in the Korban Pesach. Okay, so the
Gemara says רבי אומר, omer Rebbi says, אקרא אני בשל. Ekra ani
bashel. The Torah could have said just bashel. מה תלמוד לומר מבושל?
ma talmud lomar mevushal? Why does it say בשל מבושל במים? bashel
mevushal bamyim? Now, if you remember before, Rebbi was the one that
said בשל מבושל bashel mevushal is coming to tell you other liquids,
right?
That was Rebbi, right? Yes. Okay, but anyway here he's doing something
else with the Pasuk. שאלו אין לי אלא שבשלו משחשיכה. she'ilu ein
li ela shebishlo misheshachashichah. He says, okay, we know now you only
transgress if you eat it the wrong way at night. But when
did you cook it? Maybe you only transgress if it was miscooked,
right, after nightfall at the time of the eating. בשלו מבעוד יום,
bishlo mib'od yom, if you cooked it ערב פסח Erev Pesach and
you ate it on the 15th at night, מנין, minayin, how do
I know that I transgress then even if the cooking itself was
done, you know, at a different time, earlier? תלמוד לומר בשל מבושל
מכל מקום. Talmud lomar bashel mevushal mikol makom. So that's the double
language. Of course, you might say I don't need a Pasuk for
that, why would I think to make a distinction? But anyway. So
the Gemara says, והאי בשל מבושל אפקיה רבי לצלי קדר ולשאר משקים,
vehai bashel mevushal afkei Rebbi letzli keder ulish'ar mashkim, didn't we learn
on the Amud Aleph that Rebbi learns to prohibit pan roasting and
other liquids from the double language? So how here is he using
the double language to say even cooked at an earlier time? So
the Gemara says, which it does often, and if Michael was here
he would say it's not a good grammatical argument, אם כן לימא
קרא או בשל בשל או מבושל מבושל. im kein leima kra o
bashel bashel o mevushal mevushal. No, the Pasuk could have said o
bashel bashel or mevushal mevushal. It could have used the double language
in the same word. מאי בשל מבושל? mai bashel mevushal? Why does
it use a double language and use different words? שמע מינה תרתי,
shma mina tartei, to tell you you can make two drashas. One
drasha to tell you cooking with other liquids or pan roasting, and
the other drasha to tell you even cooked on the day before.
Of course grammatically, the Torah would never say bashel bashel or mevushal
mevushal, the grammar is bashel mevushal. But be that as it may.
So what have we said until now? We've said
other liquids are no good, pan roasting is no good, but there
are things that don't fall into the בשל bashel or the נא
category like totally raw or like totally turned to charcoal, and that
gets to the second half of the Pasuk of כי אם צלי
אש, ki im tzli eish, which seems to be according to the
Gemara a לאו, a negative prohibition, but a question about whether it
is lashes or not lashes, Abaye and Rava, but Tosafos as I
said said that argued that there's other ways of understanding what's going
on, certainly in the earlier Gemaras that it's a positive Mitzvah, not
a negative Mitzvah. And then we've come to say, emphasize that the
prohibition only begins at nightfall when the Mitzvah of eating the Korban
Pesach begins, that's when it is significant. Let's do one other point.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: אכלו צלי מבעוד יום חייב.
Achalo tzli mib'od yom chayav. If you ate roasted the day before
you are chayav. Now, what exactly do you transgress? We'll talk about,
but this gets to the issue about like the Gemara indicated that
you're not allowed to eat it even roasted, you're not allowed to
eat it the day before. So if you did you did transgress
something. What? We'll find out. כזית נמי משחשיכה חייב. Ke-zayit nami misheshachashichah
chayav. Or and when you ate it it cooked prepared the wrong
way, rare, that you will transgress if you did it at nightfall
like we just said. קתני צלי. Katani tzli. So the Gemara says
קתני צלי דומיא דנא. katani tzli dumya de-na. So now, when it
says if you ate it the day before roasted you transgressed, it
compared it to eating rare at the night. So meaning מה נא
בלאו. ma na be-lav. of the same way rare is a negative
prohibition, אף צלי בלאו *Af tzli b'lav*, so roasted if you ate
it too early is a negative prohibition. Where is there a negative
prohibition to eat the חמץ *Chametz*, to eat the חמץ *Chametz*, to
eat the פסח *Pesach* before nightfall? So בשלמא נא *Bishlama na* by
the case of rare, I know where there is a negative prohibition.
It says אל תאכלו ממנו נא *Al tochlu mimenu na*, אלא צלי
מנלן *ela tzli minalan*? Where do I know that there is a
negative prohibition? I mean, I could say it's not the positive מצוה
*mitzvah* of eating the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. ואכלו את הבשר בלילה
הזה *V'achlu et habasar balaila hazeh*, מקראית *mikrait*, you should eat the
meat at this night, makes it very clear the positive מצוה *mitzvah*
begins at night. And I could say that if you did it
the day before, you've transgressed, been מבטל *mevatel* the positive מצוה *mitzvah*.
But where do I know that there is a negative prohibition of
eating it the day before? So דכתיב *Dichtiv*, of course the verse
says ואכלו את הבשר בלילה הזה *V'achlu et habasar balaila hazeh*, they
will eat, they shall eat the meat this night. בלילה אין ביום
לא *Balaila in beyom lo*, so only at night, sort of like
the פסוק *pasuk* I quoted, right? What was the פסוק *pasuk* I
quoted?
I forget the פסוק *pasuk* I just quoted. Anyway, but it's a
positive מצוה *mitzvah*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, one minute, האי
לאו הבא מכלל עשה הוא *Hai lav haba m'klal aseh hu*. That's
a negative prohibition meaning implicitly saying don't do it the day before,
but it's inferred from a positive מצוה *mitzvah*, the positive מצוה *mitzvah*
of eating it at night. Okay, וכל לאו הבא מכלל עשה עשה
*V'chol lav haba m'klal aseh aseh*, and any negative, any don't do
that's derived from a positive, eat it at night, is has a
category of a positive. You would not be considered to have transgressed
a negative. So אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda* says רב חסדא
*Rav Chisda*, הא מני רבי יהודה היא *Ha mani Rebbe Yehuda hi*.
This is רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* and we will continue tomorrow to
find out where, what thing רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* said that basically
says that if you do something that's inferred that you should not
do and it's inferred from a positive, you would still be considered
to have transgressed a negative prohibition. Okay, so I will leave you
as a cliffhanger. We'll find out
tomorrow.
Bye.